Guide to the New-York Historical Society Management Committee Records 1804-1938 NYHS-RG 1
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society management committee records
1804-1938
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society. Executive Committee
NYHS-RG 1
15 Linear feet in 31 volumes, 25 document boxes, and three oversize folders
The New-York Historical Society management committee records group includes records associated with the organization's governance structure of 1804-1937. The record group includes minute books from the meetings of the Society's members (1804-1937) and from the meetings of the Executive Committee (1842-1937), as well as from other committees and the first year (1938) of the newly-constituted Board of Trustees. The record group also includes files of so-called official papers, which include ad hoc committee reports, draft annual reports, correspondence, financial information, membership nominations, and other material directly related to the proceedings of the Society and Executive Committee meetings. Select documents have been digitized and are in the process of being made available on-line; currently available materials can be accessed via links in the finding aid.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Biographical/Historical Note
From its founding in 1804 until late 1937, when a corporate governance structure with a Board of Trustees was established, the New-York Historical Society (N-YHS) was governed by its general membership. Although N-YHS's Constitution and By-Laws were revised many times, for over one hundred years, until 1917, regular meetings of the members were required to be held at least quarterly. Special meetings were also often called. At these meetings, in addition to hearing presentations on historical and other topics or conducting a special event, business matters were considered by the members present, such as accepting new members, considering major purchases, accepting donations, establishing collection access policies, and overseeing activities related to the collections and other aspects of the organization. At the January meeting of each year, the members held their annual election for officers, who served one year terms, and named members to the standing committees.
Although the general membership deliberated and voted on business matters at their meetings, many matters were referred to either standing or ad hoc committees for consideration and for reporting back to the membership. Of the standing committees, the most longstanding and ultimately most important was the Executive Committee. Created in November 1842, the Executive Committee lasted for the next ninety years, until it was replaced by the newly formed Board of Trustees in the organizational restructuring of November 1937. Over its lifetime, an increasing degree of responsibility was placed with the Executive Committee. By the 1890s, all standing committees existed as subcommittees of the Executive, including the Committees on Finance, Papers (called Lectures, beginning 1913), Library, Publications, Anniversary, Building, Fine Arts, and Membership (after 1917).
Standing committees other than the Executive existed at various times during the nineteenth century. In some instances, the Constitution and By-Laws were amended to specifically require the named committee. One of these was the Committee on Fine Arts, which was formed in March 1856 for the purpose of expanding N-YHS's holdings in that regard; the committee lasted until May 1895 when it was deleted from the N-YHS governing documents and replaced by a sub-committee of the Executive Committee. Various committees related to buildings, including fundraising and construction oversight, were formed in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries. A Field Exploration Committee, headed by William L. Calver, existed from 1918 to 1937 for the purpose of conducting archaeological digs and other field research. N-YHS's founding Constitution included a so-called Standing Committee, elected by the members, to solicit donations and develop plans for N-YHS's operations; this committee lasted until 1829. In 1817, various committees, including one on mineralogy, were formed as N-YHS expanded its collecting focus.
In addition to standing committees, through the nineteenth century, and especially in the earliest decades, ad hoc, or short term, committees of two or more members would be formed at the member meetings for the purpose of pursuing various specific initiatives. These initiatives included, among other things, making arrangements for a given year's anniversary celebration speaker, negotiating for available manuscript collections, overseeing production of a publication or building construction, or auditing the Treasurer's accounts. Over time, the Executive Committee absorbed these functions, but in any case it was the membership that conducted these affairs. Indeed, into the early decades of the twentieth century, N-YHS had less than ten staff members, most of whom were responsible for library support, facilities maintenance, or clerical work. Much of the managerial level work was carried out by the elected officers, especially by the Librarian, who acted as something of a chief operating officer and was responsible for N-YHS's entire range of collections and activities.
Despite the growing importance of the Executive Committee, until 1917 much business was still brought to the regular member meetings for discussion and final resolution. In 1917, N-YHS's Constitution and By-Laws were amended to place virtually all governance and management powers with the Executive Committee, which comprised all N-YHS officers and twelve other members named by the President. The general membership's role in business matters was consequently reduced, mostly to electing officers. This role, too, had been reduced. Prior to 1914, these elections were held annually, at the regular January meeting; beginning with the 1914 election, the terms of office were extended to three years. Consequently, with a 3-year election cycle and the Executive Committee's increased authority in place, regular membership business meetings were held only every three years after 1917. This cycle lasted until the governance changes of 1937, which ended the participation, however limited in practical effect, of the members in the management of the Society and converted the Executive Committee into an independent Board of Trustees.
(Principal sources for the above were R.W.G. Vail's Knickerbocker Birthday, N-YHS's Annual Reports, and the records themselves.)
Scope and Contents Note
The New-York Historical Society management committee records group (NYHS-RG 1) includes records associated with the organization's governance structure of 1804-1937. The record group includes ten volumes of minute books from the meetings of the Society's members (1804-1937) and twenty volumes of minute books from the Executive Committee (1842-1937). The final volume of the Executive Committee minutes also includes the minutes for the 1938 meetings of the newly-formed Board of Trustees. The record group also holds the minute books for three other committees: the Standing Committee (1806-1822, with gaps), the Mineralogical Committee (1818-1819), and the Committee on Fine Arts (1856-1880). The Standing Committee book includes mostly lists of donations to N-YHS for many of these early years.
The record group also includes so-called "official papers" (1804-1938). Most of these papers are preparatory material for the Society and Executive Committee meetings, preliminary notes and drafts of meeting minutes, or supporting or source materials concerning matters presented at the meetings, such as correspondence, reports, invoices, nominations of new members, and so forth. Taken together, the minute books and the supporting official papers form the framework of the basic narrative of the history of N-YHS to 1938.
Related Archival Materials Note
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the New-York Historical Society archives. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Archives (NYHS-RG Archives). Other record groups that are processed and available to researchers and are especially related to the New-York Historical Society management committee records (NYHS-RG 1) are as follows:
Although this management committee record group holds reports and includes references in the minute books to the work of the various buildings committees active in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries to 1938, most material on the subject of building construction, including several standalone committee minute books, will be found in the New-York Historical Society original buildings planning & construction records (NYHS-RG 3).
For the early to mid-nineteenth century records, there is not a consistently sharp distinction between the content of the official papers and of the correspondence files that were maintained by N-YHS. Accordingly, researchers should also see New-York Historical Society general correspondence (NYHS-RG 2).
In late 1937, N-YHS changed its organizational structure from a member-governed one to one governed by a Board of Trustees. The 1938 Board records were maintained in the same volumes and files as those of the previous governing body, the Executive Committee, and so are found here in NYHS-RG 1. Subsequent Board records from 1939 and later are found in a different record group (NYHS-RG 18).
Arrangement Note
The New-York Historical Society management committee records (NYHS-RG 1) record group is organized in 4 series:
Series I. Society Meeting Minutes (1804-1937)
Series II. Executive Committee Minutes (1843-1938)
Series III. Other Committee Minutes (1806-1822, 1856-1880)
Series IV. Official Papers (1805-1938)
Existence and Location of Copies
With the generous support of the Leon Levy Foundation, the minute books from the record group (30 volumes) were digitized in 2019-2020. Metadata is currently being applied to these images and the volumes are being made available on-line as each is completed. The on-line images can be accessed via links in the finding aid and from within the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
Accounts.; Annual reports.; Letters (correspondence); Membership lists.; Minute books.; Receipts (financial records); New York (N.Y.) -- History -- Societies, etc.; Learned institutions and societies -- New York (State) -- New York -- Management.; Libraries and institutions -- New York (State) -- New York -- Management.; Museums -- New York (State) -- New York -- Management.; New-York Historical Society -- Archives.; New-York Historical Society -- Management.; New-York Historical Society. Executive Committee
- Series I. Society Meeting Minutes, 1804-1937; 1.6 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents Note
  The Society Meeting Minutes series includes the ten bound volumes of minutes recorded at the regular and special meetings of N-YHS members from its founding meeting on November 20, 1804, to the last of these meetings on November 16, 1937. Although there is a degree of consistency in the content of the meeting entries over the years, there are also many differences. Some of these differences are likely clerical in nature, such as the tendencies or thoroughness of the various recording secretaries. Some differences relate to the changing scope of the matters brought for consideration and vote to the Society meetings; by the early twentieth century, most business matters were handled within the Executive Committee (see Series II). After the constitutional amendments of 1917, only a few matters other than officer elections are documented in the minutes. Accordingly, the following scope notes relate principally to the meeting minutes from 1804 to 1917.
  Routine content includes lists of individuals nominated and accepted for membership; obituaries/memorials for recently-deceased members and nationally-known figures; annual elections of officers; meeting attendees; and appointments of temporary committees to consider various specific matters.
  Donations of items are recorded inconsistently. For the period from the 1820s to 1841, there are frequent detailed lists of accessions. There are references to donations before and after that period as well but, especially after 1841, other books are noted as holding this information (see the New-York Historical Society collection accession registers record group (NYHS-RG 15)). The minutes record many initiatives aimed at expanding the collection of manuscripts, artifacts, and artwork. These include successful matters, such as the acquisition of art from the New York Gallery of Fine Arts in 1857, and unfruitful ones, such as the offer from Mathew Brady of his Civil War photographs in 1866.
  Operational matters, including finances, leasing space in the early-mid 1800s, acquiring land and constructing buildings in the mid-1800s and in the 1900s, setting open hours for the rooms, and proposing constitutional and by-law amendments are recorded in the minutes. Financial matters from N-YHS's earliest years are not always recorded in any particular detail, but the amount of this information expands in later years to account for various funds, investments held, and other matters. N-YHS's financial struggles of the 1820s and 1830s, and their eventual resolution, are well-documented in the minutes.
  Reports from committees are sometimes written into the minutes in full, as is some important correspondence. These reports include those of the various buildings committees created over time. References can also be found to the ultimately unsuccessful initiative of the 1860s-1870s to locate N-YHS within Central Park (see New-York Historical Society original buildings planning & construction records (NYHS-RG 3) for much more on this topic).
  The minutes also record to some extent the educational and social activities of N-YHS. These include noting those invited to read papers to the members and the subject of those papers; decisions to publish certain material; and summaries of anniversary celebrations and other special events, sometimes noting the toasts at the event.
  Arrangement Note
  The series is arranged in chronological order, in 10 bound volumes. The minutes were bound in new covers in July 1936 by the New-York Historical Society.
  In some volumes, loose documents, such as the slates of nominated candidates for N-YHS officers, were found during processing. These were removed from the volumes and placed in a separate folder and box, which is noted in the container list below. The point in the volume from which the documents were removed is noted in the folder with the documents.
  - Minutes. Volume 1, 1804-1837 (Volume RG1.1, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents Removed from Minutes Volume 1, ca. 1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes mostly brief notes likely related to Vail's research for his N-YHS history.
  - Minutes. Volume 2, 1838-1848 (Volume RG1.2, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents Removed from Minutes Volume 2, 1843 June 14-15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes clippings related to U.S. President John Tyler's cancellation of his appointment to meet with N-YHS members.
  - Minutes. Volume 3, 1849-May 1856 (Volume RG1.3, Folder -)
  - Loose Document Removed from Minutes Volume 3, 1852 October 30 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes draft of resolutions regarding the death of Daniel Webster.
  - Minutes. Volume 4, June 1856-May 1863 (Volume RG1.4, Folder -)
  - Minutes. Volume 5, June 1863-1870 (Volume RG1.5, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents Removed from Minutes Volume 5, 1864-1865, 1867, 1869-1870 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes the slates of nominated officers for the elections of 1864, 1865, 1867, and 1869; the opposition slate of 1867; an invitation to the celebration of N-YHS's 63rd anniversary (1867); and an announcement of the upcoming publication of a memorial of Alexander Anderson, written by Benson J. Lossing (1870).
  - Minutes. Volume 6, 1871-May 1879 (Volume RG1.6, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents Removed from Minutes Volume 6, 1872-1873 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes the slate of nominated officers for 1872 and notes and extract related to the meeting of April 1, 1873.
  - Minutes. Volume 7, June 1879-1887 (Volume RG1.7, Folder -)
  - Minutes. Volume 8, 1888-1900 (Volume RG1.8, Folder -)
  - Minutes. Volume 9, 1901-1908 (Volume RG1.9, Folder -)
  - Minutes. Volume 10, 1909-November 1937 (Volume RG1.10, Folder -)
- Series II. Executive Committee Minutes, 1843-1938; 2.4 Linear feet
  The Executive Committee Meeting Minutes series includes the twenty bound volumes of minutes recorded at the meetings of the committee from April 1843 to the last of its meetings in 1937. The series also includes the 1938 minutes of the committee's successor governing body, the Board of Trustees; the 1938 minutes are bound in the same volume as the 1936-1937 committee minutes.
  Matters routinely considered by the Executive Committee and recorded in the minutes include the recommendation for election of individuals nominated for membership; consideration of publishing initiatives; vetting speakers and papers to be presented at Society meetings; review of finances and banking arrangements, including the performance of mortgages held for investment; approval of library hours and other operational matters; assessment of the condition of the collections, including the Abbott Egyptian collection, which is discussed extensively in 1916; compilation of member lists; consideration of acquisitions by purchase or by donation; approval of the payments of bills (which are listed in the minutes until sometime in the 1920s); maintenance of the buildings; permissions to photograph objects; and proposals of changes to the N-YHS Constitution and By-laws. In addition to its broad scope, the Executive Committee also worked closely with the Fine Arts Committee and the buildings committees so references to their activities are found in these minutes also. In short, the full range of management matters was conducted by the committee and is reflected in the minutes.
  The series is arranged in chronological order, in 20 bound volumes. The first twelve volumes were bound in new covers in July 1936 by the New-York Historical Society. The final volume was bound in April 1943. The other eight volumes remain in their original covers, which are somewhat deteriorated.
  In some volumes, loose documents, such as lists of standing committees, were found during processing. These were removed from the volumes and placed in a separate folder and box, which is noted in the container list below. The point in the volume from which the documents were removed is noted in the folder with the documents.
  On-line Access to Digital Copies
  With the generous support of the Leon Levy Foundation, all 20 volumes of the Executive Committee minute books were digitized in 2019-2020. Digitization of the volumes was done on-site at N-YHS by an independent photographer, Ardon Bar-Hama. Metadata is currently being applied to these images by N-YHS staff and the volumes are being made available on-line as each is completed. Links to the individual volumes can be found below in the container list. Links to all Executive Committee minute books can be found beginning at this landing page.
  Guidance for Executive Committee Minute Books Keyword Searching in the Digital Library
  In late 2019 and early 2020, the Executive Committee minute books were digitized. In preparing the metadata for these volumes, each page/image was skimmed for subject matter (in addition to page number and date), and brief summaries were added to the description field of each image. These descriptions are included in the full-text search indexing in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library. Certain specific subjects can be found directly with obvious keywords, such as Audubon (for the purchase of the drawings), Central Park (for the effort to locate the N-YHS galleries in the Park), Egyptian (for matters related to that collection), Publication Fund (for that particular publication initiative), Phoenix Fund (for purchases made over the years from that Fund), particular donor or collection names, and so forth.
  There are however many other matters that were summarized in a more general or thematic way, using consistent keywords embedded in the description to facilitate discovery in searches, or to facilitate reviews of the images when looking at individual pages. These keywords include:
  "Lecture," often used as "lecture arrangements," typically refers to making arrangements for papers to be read at Society meetings. It can refer to specific plans or attempts to schedule particular speakers, or delegation of general responsibility to a subcommittee to set a schedule. It also includes rejections of papers, or regrets from invited speakers. It can also refer to other, public lectures because references in the minutes to lectures are not always clear who the audience will be.
  "Anniversary" will return results related to making arrangements for the events marking N-YHS's anniversary, usually held in November or December. The minutes refer to the anniversary events variously over time as either a meeting or as a celebration. "Anniversary" will also generate some results for events other than the N-YHS anniversary celebration, but those particular events are more likely found in searches of their unique name (e.g. Hudson-Fulton), or most often by the keyword "commemoration". "Speaker" and "remarks" are typically used as keywords rather than the varying oration/orator, discourse, address, and other terms found in the minutes in the context of anniversaries, commemorations, and other such events.
  "Membership nominations" refers to the committee's consideration of proposed members. Most typically, the minutes include a list of the proposed members by name. "Members" or "membership" alone can generate results related to matters specifically related to membership rights, privileges, and obligations. If a woman's name was noticed while skimming the list of membership nominations, the keyword "woman" or "women" and her name(s) was included. In order to facilitate research into the history of women in the organization an attempt was made to use the keyword "woman" or "women" in other contexts as well, such as when a woman/women donated money or collection objects, requested access to the collections for research, etc.
  "By-laws" includes proposed and adopted amendments to the corporate charter, constitution, and by-laws. "Rules" is typically used to refer to operational matters (such as establishing library access privileges) or internal administration (such as Executive Committee rules).
  "Publication" will yield results concerning arrangements for publication of the Collections, annual reports, anniversary addresses, proceedings, etc. Publication Fund is a specific case of this keyword.
  "Library" is used for matters directly related to collections of books, manuscripts, maps, newspapers, etc., as well as to specific operational matters, such as hours/access, etc. and the physical library/reading room. What we now refer to as the "museum" is more complex. Generally, the early volumes distinguish between "museum" collections, meaning artifacts, and "gallery/galleries," meaning the art collection and art galleries. When the minutes are unclear, the keyword "museum" was used (including when the minutes use "cabinet" or "antiquities"). But multiple keywords can be in play in this context, including "art", "gallery" or galleries, and "museum". "Conservation" was used for the repair, relining, or other work on objects.